Guide to the Montana Legislature (48th: 1983) records 1983
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislature (48th: 1983) records
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 48
Montana. Legislature.
21.5 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains the records (1983) of the Montana 48th Legislature including minutes of the Joint Special Committee on Prison Expansion Oversight; the House Select Committee on Economic Development; minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees, House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and memorials; and miscellany of the regular and December 1983 special session. [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see MM 13-14]
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 48th Montana Legislature met from January 3rd to April 21st, 1983. The leaders of the Senate were Stan Stephens (R-President), Allen Kolstad (R-President Pro Tempore), Frank Hazellbaker (R-Majority Leader), and Chet Baylock (D-Minority Leader). The leaders of the House were Dan Kemmis (D-Speaker), Joe Brand (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), John Vincent (D-Majority Leader), and Bob Marks (R-Minority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Collection includes minutes of the Joint Special Committee on Prison Expansion Oversight; the House Select Committee on Economic Development; minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; and House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and memorials. The collection also contains miscellany material including sponsor list; Senate memorial program; proclamation (including gubernatorial call for a special session and message to the Special Session; and roll of members of the Senate.
The collection is organized into the two subgroups, Regular Session, and Special Session.
The subgroup Regular Session is organized into these four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into these three subseries, Joint Subcommittee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), and Special Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically). The series House of Representatives is organized into these nine subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Special Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), Status Sheets of Inactive House Bills (arranged chronologically), House Journals (arranged chronologically), and Subject Index to House Bills (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into these eight subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Confirmation Resolutions (arranged chronologically), Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), Senate Journals (arranged chronologically), and Subject Index to Senate Bills(arranged chronologically).
The subgroup Special Session is organized into these three series, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany. The series House of Representatives is organized into these six subseries, Joint Committees and Conference Committees (arranged chronologically), House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), and House Journals (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into five subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), and Senate Journals (arranged chronologically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
Audio recordings on cassette: OVERSIZE MATERIAL see MM 13-14
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Committees--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Regular Session
  - House and Senate Joint Committees
    - Joint Subcommittee Minutes
      - Appropriations: Education Subcommittee, 1983 January 3 - April 11 (Box-folder 1 / 1-8)
      - Appropriations: Education Subcommittee (exhibits), 1983 January-April (Box-folder 1 / 9)
      - Appropriations: Highways and Elected Officials Subcommittee, 1983 January 6 - February 7 (Box-folder 1 / 10-14)
      - Appropriations: Highways and Elected Officials Subcommittee, 1983 February 8 - March 10 (Box-folder 2 / 1-7)
      - Appropriations: Human Services Subcommittee, 1983 January 6 - February 18 (Box-folder 2 / 8-13)
      - Appropriations: Human Services Subcommittee, 1983 February 21 - March 5 (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
      - Appropriations: Institutions Subcommittee, 1983 January 6 - February 21 (Box-folder 3 / 3-7)
      - Appropriations: Natural Resources and Business Regulation Subcommittee, 1983 January 6 - March 7 (Box-folder 3 / 8-13)
    - Joint Committee Minutes
      - Long-Range Building, 1983 February 1 - March 4 (Box-folder 3 / 14-16)
      - Long-Range Building, 1983 March 29 - April 13 (Box-folder 4 / 1-3)
      - Rules, 1983 January 21 - April 20 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Special Joint Committee Minutes
      - Prison Expansion Oversight, 1983 June 2 - 1984 November 20 (Box-folder 4 / 5-6)
  - House of Representatives
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1983 January 10 - March 21 (Box-folder 4 / 7-9)
      - Appropriations, 1983 January 4 - March 23 (Box-folder 4 / 10-17)
      - Appropriations, 1983 March 23 - March 21 (Box-folder 5 / 1-3)
      - Business and Industry, 1983 January 4 - March 30 (Box-folder 5 / 4-9)
      - Education, 1983 January 6 - April 15 (Box-folder 5 / 10-14)
      - Fish and Game, 1983 January 29 - March 17 (Box-folder 5 / 15-16)
      - Fish and Game, 1983 January 29 - March 17 (Box-folder 6 / 1-3)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1983 January 4 - April 14 (Box-folder 6 / 4-6)
      - Human Services, 1983 January 10 - April 15 (Box-folder 6 / 7-15)
      - Judiciary, 1983 January 4 - February 16 (Box-folder 7 / 1-8)
      - Judiciary (petitions regarding HB 677, legalization of cash prizes in bingo and keno games), 1982 December 20 - 1983 February 16 (Box-folder 7 / 9-10)
      - Judiciary, 1983 February 17 - April 19 (Box-folder 7 / 11-15)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1983 January 18 - April 19 (Box-folder 8 / 1-5)
      - Legislative Administration, 1982 December 15 - 1983 March 26 (Box-folder 8 / 6)
      - Natural Resources, 1983 January 10 - March 14 (Box-folder 8 / 7-10)
      - Natural Resources (petitions regarding HB 893, HB 894, opposing coal slurry pipelines and sales of water for transport of coal), 1983 March 16 (Box-folder 8 / 11)
      - Natural Resources, 1983 March 16 - April 15 (Box-folder 8 / 12-13)
      - Rules, 1983 January 11 - April 12 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
      - State Administration, 1983 January 4-14 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
      - State Administration, 1983 January 17 - April 16 (Box-folder 9 / 1-7)
      - Taxation, 1983 January 4 - March 11 (Box-folder 9 / 8-15)
      - Taxation, 1983 March 8 - April 12 (Box-folder 10 / 1-3)
    - House Special Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Economic Development, 1983 January 26 - April 15 (Box-folder 10 / 4-7)
    - House Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-160, 1983 (Box-folder 10 / 8-23)
      - Bill nos. 161-450, 1983 (Box-folder 11 / 1-31)
      - Bill nos. 451-770, 1983 (Box-folder 12 / 1-32)
      - Bill nos. 771-928, 1983 (Box-folder 13 / 1-17)
    - House Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-5, 1983 (Box-folder 13 / 18)
    - House Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-47, 1983 (Box-folder 13 / 19-21)
    - Status Sheets of House Bills
      - 2nd-69th Legislative Days, 1983 January 4 - March 26 (Box-folder 13 / 22-28)
      - 70th-90th Legislative Days, 1983 March 28 - April 21 (Box-folder 14 / 1-2)
    - Status Sheets of Inactive House Bills
      - 52nd-87th Legislative Days, 1983 March 7 - April 18 (Box-folder 14 / 3)
    - House Journals
      - 1st-90th Legislative Days, 1983 January 3 - April 21 (Box-folder 14 / 4-10)
    - Subject Index to House Bills
      - Subject Index, 1983 February 21 (Box-folder 14 / 11)
      - Supplement to Subject Index, 1983 April 11 (Box-folder 14 / 12)
  - Senate
    - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1983 January 10 - April 14 (Box-folder 14 / 13-17)
      - Business and Industry, 1983 January 7 - February 16 (Box-folder 14 / 18-20)
      - Business and Industry, 1983 February 17 - April 12 (Box-folder 15 / 1-5)
      - Education and Culture Resources, 1983 January 12 - April 10 (Box-folder 15 / 6-12)
      - Finance and Claims, 1983 January 7 - April 7 (Box-folder 15 / 13-16)
      - Finance and Claims, 1983 April 7-19 (Box-folder 16 / 1-5)
      - Fish and Games, 1983 January 20 - March 22 (Box-folder 16 / 6-9)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1983 January 13 - March 24 (Box-folder 16 / 10-12)
      - Judiciary, 1983 January 4 - February 14 (Box-folder 16 / 13-16)
      - Judiciary, 1983 February 15 - April 15 (Box-folder 17 / 1-4)
      - Judiciary (exhibits "B" and "C": petitions in support of permitting cash prizes in bingo and keno games), 1983 March 21 (Box-folder 17 / 5-7)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1983 January 6 - April 12 (Box-folder 17 / 8-11)
      - Legislative Administration, 1982 November 30 - 1983 April 20 (Box-folder 17 / 12)
      - Natural Resources, 1983 January 10 - April 19 (Box-folder 17 / 13-16)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 1983 January 10 - March 24 (Box-folder 18 / 1-6)
      - Rules, 1983 January 8 - April 20 (Box-folder 18 / 7)
      - State Administration, 1983 January 6 - April 21 (Box-folder 18 / 8-16)
      - Taxation, 1983 January 7 - April 20 (Box-folder 19 / 1-11)
    - Senate Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-100, 1983 (Box-folder 19 / 12-15)
      - Bill nos. 101-317, 1983 (Box-folder 20 / 1-21)
      - Bill nos. 318-465, 1983 (Box-folder 21 / 1-10)
    - Senate Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-5, 1983 (Box-folder 21 / 11)
    - Senate Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-26, 1983 (Box-folder 21 / 12-13)
    - Senate Confirmation Resolutions
      - Confirmation Resolutions, 1983 (Box-folder 21 / 14-15)
    - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
      - 1st-70th Legislative Days, 1983 January 3 - March 28 (Box-folder 21 / 16-20)
      - 71st-90th Legislative Days, 1983 March 29 - April 21 (Box-folder 22 / 1)
    - Senate Journals
      - 1st-90th Legislative Days, 1983 January 3 - April 21 (Box-folder 22 / 2-6)
    - Subject Index to Senate Bills
      - Subject Index, 1983 (Box-folder 22 / 7)
  - Miscellany
    - Sponsor list; Senate Memorial program, 1983 April (Box-folder 22 / 8)
- Special Session
  - House of Representatives
    - Joint Committees and Conference Committees
      - Joint Committee Audio Recordings [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see MM 13], 1983
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, 1983 December 14 (Box-folder 22 / 9)
      - Appropriations, 1983 December 12-16 (Box-folder 22 / 10)
      - Judiciary, 1983 December 12-15 (Box-folder 22 / 11-12)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1983 December 16 (Box-folder 22 / 13)
      - Taxation, 1983 December 16 (Box-folder 22 / 14)
    - House Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-11, 1983 (Box-folder 22 / 15)
    - House Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-2, 1983 (Box-folder 22 / 16)
    - Status Sheets of House Bills
      - 1st-2nd, 4th Legislative Days, 1983 December 12-13, 15 (Box-folder 22 / 17)
    - House Journals
      - 1st-2nd Legislative, 1983 December 12-13 (Box-folder 22 / 18)
  - Senate
    - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
      - Finance and Claims, 1983 December 13-15 (Box-folder 22 / 19)
      - Judiciary [OVERSIZE MATERIAL: see MM 14], 1983 December 13-16 (Box-folder 22 / 20)
      - State Administration, 1983 December 14-16 (Box-folder 22 / 21)
      - Taxation, 1983 December 16 (Box-folder 22 / 22)
    - Senate Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-3, 1983 (Box-folder 22 / 23)
    - Senate Resolutions
      - Bill no. 1, 1983 (Box-folder 22 / 24)
    - Senate Joint Resolution
      - Bill no. 25, 1983 December 13-15 (Box-folder 22 / 25)
    - Senate Journals
      - 1st-2nd, 4th Legislative Days, 1983 December 12-13, 15 (Box-folder 22 / 26)
  - Miscellany
    - Proclamations (include gubernatorial call for a special session and message to the Special Session), 1983 December 13, 22 (Box-folder 22 / 27)
    - Roll of the members of the Senate, 1983 December 12 (Box-folder 22 / 28)